A Guide to the Kenneth C. Smithburn Papers FA040
Rockefeller Archive Center
Kenneth C. Smithburn papers
1922-1974 (bulk 1938-1959)
bulk
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Medicine and Public Health
Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division
Rockefeller Foundation
Rockefeller University
Smithburn, Kenneth C.
Kitchen, Stuart
Haddow, A. J. (Alexander John)
Sabin, Albert B. (Albert Bruce)
United States. Army Epidemiological Board
Kokernot, Robert H.
United States. Army
United States. Armed Forces
Strode, George K.
FA040
6.4 Cubic Feet
Arrangement note
The papers are arranged in four series:
Series 1 - Subject Files
Series 2 - Professional Diaries
Series 3 - Personal Papers
Series 4 - Printed Materials
Biographical/Historical note
Kenneth C. Smithburn was born October 19, 1904, in Noblesville, Indiana. He received the B.S. (1926) and the M.D. (1928) degrees from Indiana University.
From 1930-1938, Smithburn was a staff member of the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research in New York (later known as The Rockefeller University). In 1939, he joined the Yellow Fever Research Institute, Entebbe, Uganda, becoming director in 1946, a post he held until 1948. In 1953 he organized and directed a unit for research in Johannesburg, South Africa, on arthropod-borne viruses under the joint sponsorship of the Rockefeller Foundation, the South African Institute for Medical Research, and the Poliomyelitis Research Foundation. He remained there until 1959 when he retired.
Smithburn was appointed to the Hemorrhagic Fever Commission (1952-1954), and the Virus and Rickettsial Disease Commission (1953). He was a member of the following organizations: American Association of Immunologists, American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene, and the Royal Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. He was a fellow of the New York Academy of Sciences and an honorary member of the British Medical Association.
Smithburn was a prolific writer publishing both individually and jointly over ninety monographs. Subjects covered in these publications include: meningococcal disease, meningitis, anemias, experimental tuberculosis, epidemiology of yellow fever, neurotropic viruses isolated in Africa, immunological relationships between viruses, and antiviral immunity surveys.
Kenneth C. Smithburn died in Indianapolis, Indiana, on November 23, 1973.
Scope and Contents note
The Kenneth C. Smithburn papers document the career of research scientist Kenneth C. Smithburn in the identification and isolation of viruses, particularly the Yellow Fever virus in Africa. The papers also document more broadly the Foundation's interest in public health through the International Health Division and its successor, the Division of Medicine and Public Health. The papers span the years 1922 to 1974, with the bulk falling between the years 1938 through 1959.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for scholarly research, except where particular restrictions are noted.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IV 2A 15
Africa; Entebbe (Uganda); Public health; Johannesburg (South Africa); Korea; Japan; Yellow fever; Viruses -- Research; Medical research; Arboviruses; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Medicine and Public Health; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Rockefeller Foundation; Rockefeller University; Smithburn, Kenneth C.; Kitchen, Stuart; Haddow, A. J. (Alexander John); Sabin, Albert B. (Albert Bruce); United States. Army Epidemiological Board; Kokernot, Robert H.; United States. Army; United States. Armed Forces; Strode, George K.
- Subject Files, 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Series 1, Subject Files, contains Smithburn's professional correspondence and experimental data arranged in the order in which they were received. Thus, within these files, both unique and routine materials are intermingled. Information about Smithburn's appointment in 1938 to the Yellow Fever Unit in Entebbe is found in correspondence with the Rockefeller Foundation in folder 60. Correspondence with colleagues Alec Haddow (1943-1964), Stuart Kitchen (1946-1964), and Paul Maurice Weinbren (1955-1959) contain ongoing discussions of experiments and scientific findings in Entebbe following his departure in 1948. Correspondence with George Strode in 1947, located in folder 67, reveals Smithburn's concern about the impending transfer of the Entebbe Unit to London control and his desire to return to the States. A brief history of the Entebbe Unit, written by Smithburn, is located in folder 54.
  Also present in Series 1 are reports, memoranda and correspondence (folders 12, 14-16) relating to work done on behalf of the Army Epidemiological Board with Hemorrhagic Fever in Japan and Korea from 1952 to 1953. There is extensive correspondence with Robert Kokernot (1955-1973), primarily personal in nature, with early letters describing laboratory experiments in Johannesburg, South Africa. Smithburn's correspondence with the Rockefeller Foundation is of a routine nature and concerns reimbursements for supplies, salary and retirement, housing, insurance, and other personal matters.
  Scientific data and experiment files contain information on a variety of viruses, their carriers, and protocols used. A 1953 letter between Smithburn and John Craig in folder 28, discusses linkages between Japanese B Encephalitis and the arthropod-borne viruses. An epidemic similar in nature to Chikungunya disease is described in a report located in folder 4. There are nine letters from Albert B. Sabin relating to experiments with the dengue and sandfly fever viruses.
  Arrangement note
  In Series 1, the files are arranged alphabetically by name and subject.
  - American Type Culture Collection, 1957-1961, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Army Epidemiological Board, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Arthropod-borne Virus Research Unit - South Africa, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Arthropod-borne Virus Research Unit - South Africa, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Arthropod-borne Virus Research Unit - South Africa, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Belgian Congo Programs, 1940-1941, 1948, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bunyamwera Virus, 1943-1945, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bwamba Fever Viruses, 1939-1941, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cox, Herald R., 1950, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Commission on Virus and Rickettsial Disease, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Dick, George W. A., 1948-1952, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Epidemic Hemorrhagic Fever Commission - Administrative Correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Epidemic Hemorrhagic Fever Commission - Expense Records, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Epidemic Hemorrhagic Fever Commission - Reports and Memoranda, 1952-June 25, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Epidemic Hemorrhagic Fever Commission - Reports and Memoranda, 1952-June 25, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Epidemic Hemorrhagic Fever Commission - Reports and Memoranda, 1952-June 25, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Expense Accounts and Vouchers, 1941, 1948-1959 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Expense Accounts and Vouchers, 1941, 1948-1959 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Findlay, G. M., 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Gear, James H. S., 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Gould House Conference on Arthropod-borne Virus, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Hackett, Lewis W. - The American Journal of Tropical Medicine, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Haddow, Alec J., 1943-1955, 1959-1964, 1973, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Heidelberger, Michael J., 1937-1938, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Horgan, E. S., 1948, 1950, 1952, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Hughes, Thomas P., 1940, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Human Immunization, 1949-1951 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - International Health Division/Division of Medicine and Public Health Correspondence, 1949-1953 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - International Health Division/Division of Medicine and Public Health Memoranda, 1949-1955, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - International Health Division/Division of Medicine and Public Health Memoranda, 1949-1955, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Jacobs, Henry R., December 9, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Kerr, J. Austin, 1952-1955, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Kidd, John G., 1942-1972, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Kitchen, Stuart F., 1946-1953, 1959, 1961, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Kokernot, Robert H., 1955-1973 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Kokernot, Robert H., 1955-1973 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Kokernot, Robert H., 1955-1973 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Kokernot, Robert H., 1955-1973 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Lennette, Edwin H., 1951-1953 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Lumsden, W. H. Russell, 1948, 1951, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Mahaffy, Alexander Francis, 1946-1967 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Mason, Richard P., 1952-1953 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - McIntosh, Bruce M. and Worth, C. Brooke, 1958-1973 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Meillon, Botha de, 1958-1973 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Miles, John A. R., 1951-1956 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1928-1953 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1928-1953 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1928-1953 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1928-1953 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Ntaya Virus, 1943-1950 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Paul, John R., 1942, 1948-1953 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Pinner, Max, 1935-1938 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Poliomyelitis - Mauritius, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Publications - Editor's Correspondence, 1949-1962 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Rift Valley Fever, 1944-1947 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Comptroller's Office, 1958-1963 (Box 6, Folder 56)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted - Confidential material.
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Director's Correspondence, 1957-1970 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Director's Correspondence, 1957-1970 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Director's Correspondence, 1957-1970 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Personnel Matters, 1938-1954 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Personnel Matters, 1938-1954 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Personnel Matters, 1938-1954 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Personnel Matters, 1955-1958 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Salary and Retirement, 1938-1967 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Salary and Retirement - Monthly Statements, 1938-1952 (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Salary and Retirement - Monthly Statements, 1938-1952 (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Virus Program, 1947-1951 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Ross, R. William, 1950, 1952, 1959, 1964, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Sabin, Albert B., 1945, 1950-1953, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Semliki Forest Virus - Experiments, 1942-1944 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - "Semliki Forest Virus" - Manuscript Draft, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Sixth International Congress of Tropical Medicine and Malaria, Lisbon, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Smadel, Joseph E., 1946-1963 (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - Talks and Lectures, 1949-1954 (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - Talks and Lectures, 1949-1954 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Taylor, Richard M., 1949-1973, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Taylor, Richard M., 1949-1973, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Taylor, Richard M., 1949-1973, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Taylor, Richard M., 1949-1973, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - Technique Book - Pages 1-145, ca. 1922-1938 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Technique Book - Pages 1-145, ca. 1922-1938 (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - Technique Book - Experiments, pp 83-140, ca. 1922-1938 (Box 9, Folder 82)
  - Virus Research Institute, Entebbe, 1949-1953 (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Virus Research Notes - South Africa, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 84)
  - Viruses - Miscellaneous, 1942-1955 (Box 9, Folder 85)
  - Viruses - Miscellaneous, 1942-1955 (Box 9, Folder 86)
  - Viruses - Miscellaneous, 1942-1955 (Box 9, Folder 87)
  - Warren, Andrew J., 1939-1946, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 88)
  - Weinbren, Paul Maurice, 1955-1959 (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - Weinbren, Paul Maurice, 1955-1959 (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - Weinbren, Paul Maurice, 1960-1970 (?) (Box 10, Folder 91)
  - Weinbren, Paul Maurice, 1960-1970 (?) (Box 10, Folder 92)
  - West Nile Virus, 1939-1943 (Box 10, Folder 93)
  - World Health Organization - Expert Advisory Panel on Virus Diseases, 1959-1964 (Box 10, Folder 94)
  - World Health Organization - Expert Advisory Panel on Yellow Fever, 1952-1960 (Box 10, Folder 95)
  - Yellow Fever Experiments - Protection Tests and Vaccines, 1938-1950 (Box 10, Folder 96)
  - Yellow Fever Experiments - Susceptibility of African Wild Animals, 1942-1948 (Box 10, Folder 97)
  - Yellow Fever Experiments - Sentinel Program - Aedes Africanus, 1948-1949, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 98)
  - Zerfas, L. G., 1932-1937 (Box 10, Folder 99)
- Professional Diaries, 2
  Series 2, Professional Diaries, contains Smithburn's personal copies (handwritten) of the diaries he kept on a daily basis while in Africa. Typed copies of the diaries and monthly summaries were sent to the Rockefeller Foundation on a regular basis. These are located in the Rockefeller Foundation Archives, Record Group 12.1, Box 56. There is a gap for the period from 1949 through most of 1953, during which time Smithburn worked in the New York offices.
  In Series 2, diaries are arranged chronologically.
  - November 19, 1938 - April 15, 1939 - Manuscript Typescript, 1938-1939 (Box 11, Folder 100)
  - November 19, 1938 - May 17, 1939, 1938-1939; 1 volume (Box 11, Folder 101)
  - May 17, 1939 (continued) - September 4, 1940, 1939-1940; 1 volume (Box 11, Folder 102)
  - September 5, 1940 - September 25, 1941, 1940-1941; 1 volume (Box 11, Folder 103)
  - May 5 - December 31, 1942, 1 volume (Box 11, Folder 104)
  - January 1 - May 7, 1943, 1 volume (Box 11, Folder 105)
  - May 8, 1943 - February 5, 1944, 1943-1944; 1 volume (Box 12, Folder 106)
  - February 6 - December 22, 1944, 1 volume (Box 12, Folder 107)
  - December 22, 1944 (continued) - January 12, 1947, 1944-1947; 1 volume (Box 12, Folder 108)
  - January 9, 1947 - July 16, 1948, 1947-1948; 1 volume (Box 12, Folder 109)
  - July 17 - December 31, 1948, 1 volume (Box 13, Folder 110)
    With loose material.
  - October 20, 1953 - December 31, 1954, 1953-1954 (Box 13, Folder 111)
    Unbound material.
  - January 1 - November 3, 1955 (Box 13, Folder 112)
  - January 1 - November 21, 1956 (Box 13, Folder 113)
  - January 1, 1957 - September 15, 1958, 1957-1958 (Box 13, Folder 114)
  - March 3, 1958 - March 2, 1959, 1958-1959; 1 volume (Box 13, Folder 115)
- Personal Papers, 3
  Series 3, Personal Papers, contains correspondence with friends and colleagues following Smithburn's retirement in 1959. A concise and thorough documentation of Smithburn's illness is contained in folder 133.
  Materials in Series 3 are arranged alphabetically by type of material and thereunder alphabetically or chronologically.
  - Awards and Memberships, 1938-1973 (Box 14, Folder 116)
  - Certificates of Identification, 1904, 1940, 1957-1961 (Box 14, Folder 117)
  - Certificates of Vaccination, 1942, 1945, 1957 (Box 14, Folder 118)
  - Correspondence - Bugher, John C., 1962-1972 (Box 14, Folder 119)
  - Correspondence - Davis, David H. S., 1959-1966 (Box 14, Folder 120)
  - Correspondence - Dowdeswell, Cecil, 1959-1972 (Box 14, Folder 121)
  - Correspondence - Hampton, John W. F., 1959-1963 (Box 14, Folder 122)
  - Correspondence - Kofsky, Rosemary, 1960-1971 (Box 14, Folder 123)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 1948-1964, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 124)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 1948-1964, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 125)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 1948-1964, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 126)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 1965-1974 (Box 15, Folder 127)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 1965-1974 (Box 15, Folder 128)
  - Correspondence - Serafini, Eugene T., 1959-1972 (Box 15, Folder 129)
  - Correspondence - Sympathy Messages (Incoming), 1959, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 130)
  - Correspondence - Trent, R. Max, 1959-1972, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 131)
  - Diplomas and Licenses, 1926, 1928-1929, 1954 (Box 15, Folder 132)
  - Emphysema - Papers Related to the Treatment of, 1952, 1955-1971 (Box 15, Folder 133)
  - Travel Diaries, 1938, 1952; 2 volumes (Box 15, Folder 134)
- Printed Materials, 4
  Series 4, Printed Materials, contains two bound volumes of Smithburn's published works. There is also a loose monograph not included in the bound volumes, entitled "Studies on Arthropod-Borne Viruses of Tongaland."
  In Series 4, printed materials are arranged chronologically.
  - "Collected Papers of Kenneth C. Smithburn", 1930-1939; 1 volume (Box 16, Folder 135)
  - "Collected Papers of Kenneth C. Smithburn", 1940-1961; 1 volume, 1 reprint (Box 16, Folder 136)